Guide to the Maury Maverick, Jr. Papers
The Wittliff Collections
Maury Maverick, Jr. Papers
1920-2003
The Wittliff Collections https://www.thewittliffcollections.txstate.edu
Maverick, Maury (Fontaine Maury), 1921-2003
SWWC.136
3.5 Linear Feet
6 boxes
Printed material, correspondences, photographs, scrapbooks, awards, personal files, 1920's to 2003, document the life and activities of Maury Maverick Jr. Organized into series for photographs, correspondences, biographical material, Israel, and written works by Maverick.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Julia Maverick, 2016
Biographical Note
Maury Maverick Jr. (1921-2003) was a member of the prominent San Antonio Maverick family who traces their lineage back to the Texas Revolution. Throughout his life, Maverick worked as a lawyer, politician, and activist. He served in the Marine Corps during World War II after which he got his law degree. In 1950, following in his father's footsteps, he was elected as a Democrat to the Texas House of Representatives where he supported workers rights and civil rights. He also opposed the persecution of suspected communists during the Red Scare.
In the 1960s, Maverick left his political career and went to work for the American Civil Liberties Union where he represented civil rights activists, communists, and those opposing the Vietnam War. He left his legal career in 1980 and became a columnist for the San Antonio Express News where he continued to write in support of civil rights and worker's rights. He faced backlash later in his career from the Jewish community in Texas for his support of Palestine in the Palestinian and Israeli conflict. This collection mainly consists of documents from this time in his life forward. He stayed with the San Antonio Express News until his death in 2003. His last column was a condemnation of the Iraq War. He is remembered for his activism, and a San Antonio library was built in his honor.
Scope and Contents
Printed material, correspondences, photographs, scrapbooks, awards, personal files, 1920's to 2003, document the life and activities of Maury Maverick Jr. Organized into series for photographs, correspondences, biographical material, Israel, and written works by Maverick. Within the photographic series there are family photographs, photos of Maury Maverick Sr. with prominent political figures such as Lyndon Baines Johnson, military photographs, and photos from the life of Maury Maverick Jr.
The correspondences series consists of correspondences written to Maverick, correspondences about Maverick, and correspondences from Maverick. The biographical material series is the largest series of works, consisting of scrapbooks, information on his death including funeral programs and newspaper articles, collected newspaper clippings, military papers, a personal account book, awards and certificates, collected items from travels such as a tote bag and a book, and published works written about Maury Maverick Jr.
Of note is the Israel series, which consists of newspaper clippings, letters, opinion pieces, and notes by and about Maverick and his advocacy for Palestine in the Israeli-Palestinian conflict. This scope of this series is between 1992 and 1998. The final series is a collection of much of the work published by Maury Maverick Jr. in the San Antonio Express News between the 1980's and 2003, as well as some personal research he used when writing pieces and working as a lawyer. Not present in the collection is his work and papers as a lawyer during the 1960's and 1970's nor his papers from when he was active in politics in between the 1940's and 1960's.
Index Terms
Subjects
Arab-Israeli conflict
Document Types
Journalism -- Texas
Subjects (Persons)
Maverick, Maury (Fontaine Maury), 1921-2003
- Photographs, circa 1920-2000
  Series Description
  This series includes family photographs, photos of Maury Maverick Sr. with prominent political figures such as Lyndon Baines Johnson, military photographs, and photos from the life of Maury Maverick Jr..
  - Unidentified photographs (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Maury Maverick, Jr. with others (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Maury Maverick, Sr. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Family, 1920s-2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Maury Maverick, Jr., 1940s-2000s (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1959-2003
  The correspondences series consists of letters written to, about, and from Maverick.
  - Correspondences about Maverick, 1965-2003 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondences from Maverick, 1974-1998 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondences to Maverick, 1959-2002 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Biographical Materials
  The biographical material series is the largest series of works, consisting of scrapbooks, information on his death including funeral programs and newspaper articles, collected newspaper clippings, military papers, a personal account book, awards and certificates, collected items from travels such as a tote bag and a book, and published works written about Maury Maverick Jr.
  - Scrapbook, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Death of Maverick, 2003
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Photocopies of newspaper articles (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Funeral programs (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Printed articles and email about death (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Military Papers, 1938-1995 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Printed Materials, 1994, undated (Box 3, Folder 2-4)
    Contents
    Newspaper clippings, printed material, and a copy of Nucleaus magazine (1994)
  - Personal Files, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Awards, 1987, 1991
    - Professional Recognition Certificates, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Mayoral Appointment Award, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Publications about Maverick, 1962-2003 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Israel, 1992-1998 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  The Israel series consists of newspaper clippings, letters, opinion pieces, and notes by and about Maverick and his advocacy for Palestine in the Israeli-Palestinian conflict.
- Writings by Maverick, 1980-2003
  This series is comprised of writings published by Maury Maverick Jr. in the San Antonio Express News between the 1980's and 2003, as well as some personal research he used when writing pieces and working as a lawyer.
  - Articles (photocopies), 1982-1995 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Articles (photocopies), 1996-2003 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Research, 1960s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Framed newspaper articles, 1983, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
  - Additional Newspaper Articles, 1981-2003, undated (Box 6, Folder 1-2)